<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Tvesha | Computer Scientist]]></title><description><![CDATA[Computer Science undergraduate with a strong passion for Machine Learning and Physics. If you need an engineer who can quickly prototype concepts and scale them up, I could be the person you’re looking for.]]></description><link>https://tveshas.github.io/tveshass</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 08:55:03 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[We Need More Women In STEM]]></title><description><![CDATA[A Global Challenge, from Silicon Valley to Remote Villages In our tech-driven era, the push for equal STEM opportunities isn’t just fair—it…]]></description><link>https://tveshas.github.io/tveshass/blog/Reflecting on leaving mechanical engineering, two years later/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://tveshas.github.io/tveshass/blog/Reflecting on leaving mechanical engineering, two years later/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;A Global Challenge, from Silicon Valley to Remote Villages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our tech-driven era, the push for equal STEM opportunities isn’t just fair—it’s vital for worldwide advancement. This mission spans from bustling tech centers to quiet hamlets in India, Pakistan, and conflict-zones like Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Afghanistan: A Battle for Basic Rights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afghan women face severe restrictions:
Schooling beyond elementary level? Forbidden.
Most jobs? Off-limits.
Dress codes and chaperone rules? Strictly enforced.
Yet, resilient Afghan women persist, embracing secret online classes and hidden learning spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Rural India and Pakistan: Battling Tradition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Village women confront:
Scarce STEM education access
Early weddings and household duties trumping careers
Age-old beliefs discouraging professional ambitions
Still, local initiatives and aid groups are making headway, bringing tech and STEM learning to these areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Global STEM Landscape: A Picture of Inequality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The numbers tell a troubling tale:
Engineering? Only 1 in 5 students are women.
Computer science? Even fewer—less than 1 in 5.
Paychecks? Men pocket $85K yearly; women, just $61K.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why the Gap Persists&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key factors include:
Old-fashioned stereotypes
Too few relatable role models
Education hurdles
Social expectations favoring homemaking over careers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Root Causes of Gender Disparity in STEM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several factors contribute to this persistent gap:
Entrenched Stereotypes: STEM fields are often perceived as masculine domains, a view that takes root as early as preschool.
Lack of Role Models: Girls have limited exposure to female scientists and engineers, especially women from their own cultural backgrounds.
Educational Barriers: In many regions, girls face restricted access to quality STEM education.
Cultural Expectations: Societal norms often prioritize domestic roles for women over professional pursuits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Roya Mahboob: Afghanistan’s Tech Pioneer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite facing threats from the Taliban, Roya Mahboob founded Afghan Citadel Software Company, employing numerous women. She continues to advocate for girls’ education in technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Project Drawdown: Empowering Rural Indian Women&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This initiative trains women in Punjab to install and maintain solar panels, simultaneously addressing climate change and gender inequality in STEM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Promise of Progress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investing in women’s STEM involvement—from remote villages to top labs—isn’t just about equality. It’s about tapping into a wellspring of innovation and talent. Our tech future hinges on embracing all bright minds, regardless of gender or birthplace.
The road to STEM equality is long, but united global action can create a world where a Pakistani village girl dreams of space exploration, and an Afghan woman sparks a tech revolution—not just at home, but worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>